<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the opening of the lecture at Maldon in Essex, lately established by the Lord Bishop of London in vindication of the antiquity of the doctrine of the Church of England / by William Bramston ...</title>
            <author>Bramston, William, d. 1735.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4243</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18304</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12868960</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12868960</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94785</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29214)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94785)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 731:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the opening of the lecture at Maldon in Essex, lately established by the Lord Bishop of London in vindication of the antiquity of the doctrine of the Church of England / by William Bramston ...</title>
                  <author>Bramston, William, d. 1735.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published at the request of the auditory."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XXIV, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94785:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON, PREACHED At the Opening of the LECTURE AT MALDON in ESSEX. Lately Eſtabliſhed By the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London:</hi> In Vindication Of the Antiquity of the Doctrine of the CHURCH of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> By <hi>William Bramſton,</hi> Late Fellow of <hi>Queens-College</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Rector of <hi>Woodhamwater</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> Publiſhed at the Requeſt of the Auditory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Clavell,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s. Church-Yard, MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:94785:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94785:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON, PREACHED At the opening the <hi>Wedneſday</hi> Lecture in <hi>All-Saints</hi> Church in <hi>Maldon.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts, Chap. 24. Verſe 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But this I confeſs unto thee, that after the way which they call Hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the way to my Text, I judge it a reaſonable tribute of our gratitude to our Dioceſan, to obſerve, how thoſe bleſſed Effects, and Influences of his paternal care and watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which are conſpicuous in all places of his Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, are in the moſt ſenſible manner made apparent to you, the Inhabitants of this remote, and almoſt forgotten corner of the Kingdom; and that in the occaſion of our preſent meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wherein you have reſtored to you a moſt laudable Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94785:3"/>which you have long wanted, your Weekly Lecture: In which you muſt needs acknowledge your engagements to your Biſhop, who hath made himſelf a debtor to many Brethren for your ſakes: Nor is the Benefaction its ſelf more worthy of your Gratitude, than the piety of his Lordſhips intention in this Lecture, may be commanding of your Thankfulneſs: Our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Hopes and Counſels, and Prayers, are, not only that you may have the gracious Arguments of Virtue, Patience, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and Holyneſs, without which, <hi>No Man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> unfolded, and recommended to your Practice in the moſt perſwaſive Applications; but alſo, that you may continue in all ſoundneſs of Doctrine, and become armed againſt the arts, and ſurpriſes of falſe Teachers, who do either obtrude their own Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, for the Commandments of God, or attempt to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the Affections of Men from our moſt excellent Church by falſe and unwarrantable miſinterpretations of her Doctrines. I ſay our moſt Excellent Church, which is loaded by <hi>Rome,</hi> with the imputations of Hereſie, becauſe the endeavours to ſhrowd her Members from the taint of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Defilements: And has been reviled by another ſort of miſtaken Chriſtians, as being her ſelf Popiſh, becauſe ſhe labours to preſerve the Holy Services of God clean, from the unhallow'd violence of Man's Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: Now there cannot be a greater Service done to the Church of Chriſt, than when his precious <hi>Depoſitum</hi> is kept unviolated, or to the Edification of his Faithful, than, when the Inſtructions tendered to them proceed purely from Truth and Soberneſs: This being our Biſhops (now Charitable) intention in this Lecture which I am to open, I have made choice of this paſſage of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who here anſwers the impeachment of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who had cenſured his Labours in Chriſt, his profeſſing, and propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Chriſtian Religion, (juſt as our Adverſaries of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> do all our holy Miniſtrations, and Services in the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Faith, and truth of the Bleſſed Jeſus) as a work of Hereſie, with this Confeſſion, <hi>But this I confeſs unto thee, that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94785:3"/>after the way that they call Hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my Fathers.</hi> That which I ſhall endeavour at preſent, ſhall be the vindication of the Doctrines and Meaſures of our Church, as to ſome Matters of her Faith and Practice, which are quarrelled at by our <hi>Roman</hi> Adverſaries; which, in the moſt inſolent Pomp, and diſdain, are exploded by them as Spots, and Deformities in our Reformation. <hi>Firſt,</hi> then, That wherewith they think they ſhake us moſt, is this, that we are of a new Religion, a novel and up-ſtart Church, not able to make out a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance for two of ſixteen Centuries.</p>
            <p>This I take to be the moſt gainful plea of the Crafts-men of their <hi>Diana,</hi> that by which ſhe moſt fatally allures many into the Labyrinth of her Deluſions: Certainly as to her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, the Monſtroſities of Tranſubſtantiation, Purgatory, of the Sacrifice of the Maſs, and Prayers in a ſtrange Language; theſe can have no appearances ſo beautiful and tempting, as to prove Charming in themſelves, and captivate our Souls enlighten'd by the wiſdom of the Goſpel: But when they are told they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a new Religion, a Religion not heard of in the Chriſtian World till theſe laſt two Hundred Years; this may poſſibly ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ignorant Men, and juſtly requires our Conſideration: In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering therefore this Objection, I doubt not to expoſe the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and diſappoint the impreſſions of ſuch light pretences, and manifeſt them to be no other but Noiſe and Cant. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then, if by a new Church, they mean a Church introducing a new Scheme of Faith and Belief; methinks that main part of old eſſential Verities, wherein they and we agree, together with our explicit belief of all the known Doctrines of the Scriptures, and our implicit belief of all things therein contained, may in great meaſure declare the Antiquity of ours; eſpecially ſince we retain all that Faith, and religiouſly adhere to all thoſe Creeds, which the third General Council held at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> adjudged to be ſo material and comprehenſive, as poſitively to forbid the impoſition or addition of any other, if that was the Old Faith
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94785:4"/>which was profeſſed by the Primitive Fathers of that Council, how can ours now be denominated a new one, who have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diminiſhed nor added to the Articles of their Belief? The Creeds confirmed, and authorized in that Council, were that of the Apoſtles, and that of <hi>Nice,</hi> and therefore methinks the Faith founded on them may with ſome face pretend to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity.</p>
            <p>Again, if by a new Church, they mean a National Church of but late Strength and Eſtabliſhment; we deny not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church of <hi>England</hi> to be a new Church in ſuch a ſenſe; but then we anſwer withal, that ſuch a new Church may be ſaid, without a Paradox, to contain as Old a Religion as the ancienteſt foundation of Chriſt, though not for the Age of its Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet for the Antiquity of its Truths and Doctrines, which only (properly ſpeaking) can Entitle any National Church a part of the ancient Church of Chriſt: And this is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt mark of Antiquity our Church pretends to aſſume, that ſhe now profeſſes that very Faith which our Saviour taught, which his Holy Apoſtles profeſs'd, and propagated in the firſt Ages of Chriſtianity. And let Men pretend what they will, the only Demonſtration and Teſt of any particular Churches Antiquity (as it is a true or a corrupted part of the Catholick Church of Chriſt) muſt be the Antiquity of her Doctrines and Principles, by reaſon as no Chriſtian Church can be ancienter than Chriſt, the Author and Finiſher of our Faith: So again, no particular Church, profeſſing his ancient Faith and Truths, can be ſaid to introduce, or embrace a Religion younger than that of Chriſt, becauſe it then profeſſes that very truth of Chriſt, which has been profeſſed by his Faithful in all Ages: So that though the Church of <hi>England</hi> may be later than the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in ſuch reſpects as theſe; either, becauſe our Converſion to the Faith might poſſibly have been after theirs; or again, becauſe our particular eſtabliſhment, as it now ſtands, was enacted many Ages ſince the firſt ſettlement
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94785:4"/>of a Chriſtian Church at <hi>Rome:</hi> Yet our Religion now may be ancienter ſtill, than their's at preſent; if they are now chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and degenerated (as 'tis demonſtrable they are) from that Chriſtian Purity, which anciently denominated them an uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted part of the Catholick Church; and we now faithfully adhere with all Uprightneſs and Integrity (which we are ready to make appear we do) to that Faith of Chriſt which was once delivered to the Saints; and as by many other Churches, ſo anciently maintain'd by the Church at <hi>Rome:</hi> For, as their new corruptions, and additional definitions of Faith muſt fall ſhort of thoſe Ages wherein Chriſtianity flouriſhed with all Truth and Purity; and thoſe can be no other than the Days of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles; ſo the old truths retained and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by us, muſt have been then moſt triumphant and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing. And therefore that which has puzzled ſo many weak and unlearned People of our Communion, to wit, the queſtion about the Age of our Religion, and our Church, may eaſily be reſolved if they diſtinguiſh the Antiquity of Seat and Place (which is nothing to the buſineſs) from the Antiquity of Truths and Doctrines; and this diſtinction muſt be allowed good even by our Adverſaries themſelves, if they conſider, that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute now is not about the Antiquity of particular Sees and national Conſtitutions, but the Antiquity of Faith and Religion its ſelf, which I hope may be the ſame in a Church of Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day's Converſion, as it was in <hi>Antioch,</hi> which had the honour to give the firſt Name to Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Did the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at any time eſteem her own Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity leſſened, upon ſuch a Conſideration as this, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> erected his Apoſtolical Seat firſt at <hi>Antioch,</hi> before ever he had arrived at <hi>Rome?</hi> Or will ſhe acknowledge a deference due to that Church in point of Faith and Purity, becauſe ſhe had the happineſs to be Chriſtened before her? I doubt the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Miſtreſs of all Churches, as ſhe delights to ſtile her ſelf, could never ſtoop to ſuch a Condeſcenſion: If my Faith
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94785:5"/>be found, and perfect now, can it be believed the more new, and up-ſtart, becauſe not profeſſed by my Fore-fathers, who knew not the Truths? Or does my late Converſion if good and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right diminiſh, or derogate from the Antiquity of Truth its ſelf? The Antiquity of all other things is calculated from their Original, and beginning in the World, and why the ſame rule won't do in Faith and Religion I underſtand not. Indeed, if any particular Church cou'd make out a continu'd Succeſſion in all circumſtances of Doctrine and Diſcipline, from the times of the Apoſtles, unto this very day, this wou'd no doubt be an incomparable Argument both of her Antiquity, and of God's eſpecial Goodneſs and Providence over her: But the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church can no more make out ſuch a Succeſſion than the preſent Church of <hi>England;</hi> and if ſhe could, ſtill ſuch a Succeſſion is not to be eſteem'd the only mark of Truth and Antiquity: And this I think cannot be more clearly illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated than from Matter of Fact, to which, we may appeal in this caſe; for inſtance, there can be no Queſtion, but the ancient Faith of Chriſt is now profeſſed by the true Faithful of Chriſt, and ſhall continue to be ſo profeſſed till the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and yet there is now no particular Church of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that can make out ſuch a Succeſſion, nor any one Church endowed with an aſſurance of continuing indefectibly in that very State in which ſhe is now, till the Day of Judgment.</p>
            <p>I know the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> wou'd fain have us believe her inſpired with theſe infallible Accompliſhments, but ſhe muſt produce a better Scheme of her Perfections, than what we meet in her <hi>Trent</hi> Definitions; or ſhe will never perſwade us, that ſhe is any more like the Church Eſtabliſh'd at <hi>Rome</hi> by St <hi>Peter,</hi> than St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf was like the moſt changed and backſliding Apoſtle: For as to her Magnificent Stile in writing her felt the Church Apoſtolick, this muſt appear rather a Character of Ornament and Shew, than any certain ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of her neceſſary continuance in Truth and Purity. For,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94785:5"/>were not the Apoſtolick Sees as liable to relapſe, and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, as any founded by their Succeſſors? Where is the glory of <hi>Antioch, Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves planted and watered with the Dew of Heaven, which thoſe Heavenly Shepherds nouriſh'd with the bleſſed Food of Evangelical Righteouſneſs? And notwithſtanding all the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſes with which the preſent <hi>Romaniſts</hi> exalt themſelves; I doubt not, but were St. <hi>Peter</hi> to ariſe this moment from the Dead, and viſit the Conclave, or inſpect the Councils of <hi>Rome,</hi> but he wou'd be very much put to it, where to find Faith on Earth.</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, her being founded by an Apoſtle (if we grant thus much) can no more Entitle her indefectible in the Faith, than it has the Churches of <hi>Antioch, Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which have either altogether failed, and forſaken the Name of Chriſt; or are (at leaſt according to their own <hi>Roman</hi> Tenents) quite cut off for Schiſm or Hereſie from the Communion of what they call the true Church; let her ſhew when, and where, God has anointed her with this Oyl of Perfection above her Fellows: But now then, if an Apoſtolick Church may thus recoil, and become impure, (nay, ſince Chriſtianity ſhall not fail) why muſt not ſome Churches be moſt pure, which yet are not Apoſtolical, I mean taught and inſtructed by the lively voice of the Apoſtles? If this be bad arguing, what may we think of all the Churches Converted, and founded many Ages ſince the days of the Apoſtles? Or, if this be a good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, what Objection can it be againſt any particular Church which is ſound, and upright in all her Doctrines, that ſhe has not continued for ever, that ſhe is yet but of a very late Birth and Duration? If her Doctrines are as Old as the Scriptures, can the Religion of ſuch a Church fall ſhort of the Age of the Goſpel? If her holy Principles flouriſhed in the ancienteſt Creeds and Councils, can ſhe reaſonably be Reproach'd for an Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Two Hundred Years ago? This is the very caſe of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94785:6"/>the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and for the truth of it, we appeal to the Scriptures, to the ancienteſt Creeds, and Councils. Indeed, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> makes a great noiſe and ſhow with the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of her Succeſſion; but if ſhe means a Succeſſion in purity of Doctrines, we may eaſily convince her of Vanity and Tattle; if ſhe means a Succeſſion in the outward circumſtances, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of a Church, ſuch as conſiſts in true Paſtors, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and the like; I anſwer, that there may be ſuch a viſible Succeſſion, and yet that Church that enjoys it in many reſpects may be very corrupt and unwarrantable; and this I think is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently acknowledg'd by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf, which does ſo far acknowledge the Succeſſion of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, as to receive thoſe Ordained by her, into her Communion, with al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of Orders received before; and yet whoever conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the terms in which the Eaſtern Church now ſtands, with that at <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt ſee little reaſon to conclude much of its Perfection, from the Argument of Succeſſion; indeed, there cannot be a true Church without true Paſtors and Biſhops, but there may be true Paſtors and Biſhops, <hi>i. e.</hi> Paſtors, and Biſhops rightly called, and truly ordained, without a true Church in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpects: Such Succeſſion will indeed prove the Antiquity of the Seat and Place, and juſtly denominate it a part of the Catholick Church of Chriſt; but it can be no convincing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the purity of its Faith and Doctrines: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt ſollow, that, even from an erroneous Church, may be derived a true Miniſtery and Ordination; but, yet it can be no greater Argument, that ſuch a particular Church, namely, as the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is a pure Church now, becauſe an other, to wit the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who is really ſo, owes her Orders or firſt Epiſcopal impoſition to hers; than it can be, that becauſe ſuch a particular Man, for his own perſonal Virtue and Integrity, ſhall certainly go to Heaven, therefore he alſo ſhall do ſo, who made him a Chriſtian: And this I the gladlier mention, becauſe it plainly anſwers that Sophiſtical Induction of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94785:6"/>which infer that, becauſe we ſay our Church derives her Orders from her; therefore by proving our ſelves to be a true Church, we muſt neceſſarily conclude their's to be ſo, which is the ſame, as if a Man in declaring his Opinion of their being Orthodox in ſome points and particulars, ſhou'd be concluded poſitively to maintain them to be moſt regular in all others. A more rational Inference from what has been ſaid in this caſe of Succeſſion, muſt certainly be this, that ſuch a Local Succeſſion of Paſtors, and a ſettled Eſtabliſhment from the days of the Apoſtles to this time, is not eſſential to the conſtitution of a true Church; but rather on the other ſide, whatever Church hath a lawful Miniſtry, and a right Profeſſion of ſound Doctrine (let her Succeſſion be never ſo inconſiderable, though not exceeding two years) muſt have an equal Right and Title to a Memberſhip in the ancient Body of Chriſt, as any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church of the moſt venerable Succeſſion: And the reaſon of the thing is very plain, for, if a Church has a true Miniſtry, and a right belief, now what ſignifies it how long ſhe has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd it; ſhe can then want no means to bring Souls to Heaven, and what advantage can the ancienteſt Conſtitution in the World obtain above her: The Seat where the Religion is ſixed may be new, but the Religion Eſtabliſh'd, as Old as Truth it ſelf: And thus I hope the Churches which were the earlieſt planted in the World, were as true Churches the firſt day after their Plantation, as when they had ſurvived various Centuries: So that it muſt be impertinent in our Adverſaries to require us to produce a Succeſſion of Proteſtant Biſhops, ſo long as there cou'd be no reaſon any Biſhops ſhou'd be called Proteſtant; <hi>i. e.</hi> Such Biſhops, who proteſt againſt Innovations and Corruptions in the Religion of Chriſt, till they had defiled God's heavenly Truths with their Traditionary Pollutions; or again, ſo long as we prove our Proteſtant Faith and Church to be no other, but a Profeſſor of that Faith, and a Member of that Apoſtolical Church, which they have Corrupted; or laſtly, ſo long as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94785:7"/>they are Corruptions introduced by them, which we diſavow, and proteſt againſt: Let them prove us defective in any one eſſential point of a true Church, and we will yet thankfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, but this their own fruitleſs endeavour towards it, may evince they cannot, and therefore to talk of Novelty and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations, where the Truths are as ancient as the Goſpel, and the Apoſtles, muſt argue great Folly in them that urge it, but more inconſideration in us ſhou'd we regard it. As we are able to juſtifie our cauſe from all their fouleſt Imputations, ſo ſhall they never be able to prove our Religion a Novelty, though its Eſtabliſhment were but of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> for it is the Antiquity of true Faith only, that we contend for, which can never be obſcured by the lateſt Profeſſion, becauſe what was truth in the Apoſtles time muſt be ſo now; and that Church, which cleaves ſtedfaſtly to that, (be its Succeſſion never ſo late) muſt be both Catholick and Apoſtolick in the pureſt meaning.</p>
            <p>After all this ſtir of Novelty and Antiquity, I ſee no other difference in our caſe, and that of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> but this, that our Religion is apparently conſpicuous in the beſt and moſt Apoſtolical Centuries; and their's manifeſt enough in the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Days of Ignorance and Superſtition, when Scriptures were baniſhed, and the leaſt appearance of ſuch Truth, as ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thwart the progreſs of an aſpiring Monarchy, was ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and diſabled: That which ſeems ſo much to take with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate Men, to wit, ſuch Queries as this, Had not God his true Church in theſe days of Blindneſs and Ignorance, which you Proteſtants allude to, if ſo, Then which cou'd be this true Church, but that at <hi>Rome,</hi> may eaſily be removed if they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <hi>Firſt,</hi> That a local and viſible Eſtabliſhment, ſuch as can be pointed to (though we have many ſuch to refer to in the Eaſtern parts of Chriſtendom, even in the blindeſt Ages, beſides that at <hi>Rome</hi>) is not eſſential to the proving of a true Church, becauſe the true Church of Chriſt was moſt illuſtrious
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94785:7"/>before it had enjoyed any Local Eſtabliſhment whatever. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> If we conſider, that though there were in thoſe times true Chriſtians, yet it cannot be imagined that they ſhould have appear'd forward to make Diſcoveries of themſelves, in ſuch Seaſons, when they experienc'd the ſharpeſt Eyes and heavieſt Hands ready to deſtroy them: So that though we muſt believe God had always a true Church, yet we ſtand not neceſſitated directly to know what numerical and individual People made up that true Church, much leſs to confeſs it to have been the preſent Eſtabliſhment at <hi>Rome;</hi> no, we can no more be oblig'd to ſuch a Confeſſion as this, than to acknowledge, that the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble company of the <hi>Jews</hi> made up the true Church of God; than, when they were even ſwallow'd up of Idolatry, and none but the All-ſeeing Eye of God able to diſcover the 7000 Knees which had never bowed to <hi>Baal;</hi> it is no Tergiverſation therefore; it is no Shuffling, I ſay (though we can't point to it's individual Members) to aſſert, That God had even then a true Church, becauſe he has expreſly told us, he will have a true Church for ever; but it muſt be a moſt irrational conſequence to conclude, that it was the <hi>Roman,</hi> when it was the <hi>Roman</hi> alone, from whence aroſe all thoſe miſty Tempeſts and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which had obſcured the Truth, nay, which had moſt grievouſly then oppreſs'd and over-born her: If we are not now able to name who thoſe good Chriſtians were, that then made up the true Church; we may thank their Furnaces, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions, and Expurgatory Subtilties, which affrighted them from the Light, and ſtill took care to ſtifle the leaſt occaſions of their manifeſtations. We confeſs, God had always his true Church, and this is agreeable to his Word, but we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge not that it was the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe ſhe was then, as ſhe is now, moſt contradictory to the Truths of his Word.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94785:8"/>
            <p>And thus I proceed to another Principle of our Church, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached of Hereſie by that of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that is our ways and methods of finding out the Truth: Now theſe are no other than what depend upon theſe two divine Principles, Scripture and Reaſon, which, as they are the immediate Gifts of God, flowing from the Excellency and Perfections of his own bleſſed Spirit, ſo methinks they may not improperly be imploy'd in his Divine Service: The Religious Man, in Scripture, is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Entituled the Wiſe and the Underſtanding Man; and Wiſdom, and Religion are generally uſed to denote one and the ſame thing, but how there can be the greateſt Wiſdom and Underſtanding where there muſt not be the leaſt uſe or pretences to Reaſon, I leave to theſe Deſpiſers of Reaſon to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. The Wiſe Man tells us, <hi>A blind Sacrifice is an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Lord,</hi> and we often meet the Holy Ghoſt in the Scriptures, laſhing at the Sacrifice of Fools, both which are demonſtratively comprehended in that rebuke of our Saviour againſt the People of <hi>Samaria,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Ye know not what ye Worſhip;</hi> and now what can all theſe Paſſages ſuggeſt to us but this, that whoſoever will pay a ſit and ſuitable Worſhip to God, ought throughly to know and underſtand the Nature and Excellency of the Divine Majeſty, as far as he has been pleaſed to reveal himſelf; and then as one wou'd think, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can more effectually inſtruct us in this Celeſtial Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, than the very Writings and expreſs Revelations of God himſelf; ſo it ſeems to me next door to a contradiction, for any Man to aver, that the moſt infallible way to come to a right Knowledge and Underſtanding of God, is to ſet aſide our Reaſon, without which, 'tis impoſſible to know or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand at all; or again, to renounce the Scriptures which are the only Books in the World, which his infallible Spirit has left us for our ſurer guidance and direction to that bleſſed Knowledge.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94785:8"/>
            <p>Perhaps, it may be ſuggeſted here, that the Myſteries and ſublime Articles of our Religion, ſuch as the Incarnation, the Trinity, and the Reſurrection, which all infinitely tranſcend the higheſt Capacities of our Reaſon, depend not on the uſe of our Reaſon, but Faith, which is of thoſe things which are inviſible, even to the moſt piercing Eye of Man's Reaſon; ſo that we muſt leave our Reaſon in the way to our embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of them, but this no way weakens the force of our Argument: For theſe Myſteries ſurpaſs indeed the compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of our Reaſon, yet the authority upon which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them into our Creed, lies open to our Reaſon, ſuch as is the voice of the Scriptures, and the example of the pureſt Ages of the Church of Chriſt; which Reaſon recommends to us as the ſureſt guides, to direct us in all Matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: And though indeed Reaſon cannot demonſtrate to us the ineffable ways and explications of theſe Truths, yet Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon furniſhes us with this Demonſtration, that they ought to be received for the Truths of Chriſt; upon this account, becauſe whatever is propoſed to our belief upon ſuch infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Evidences as the Revelation of God's Word, and the uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Authority of his Primitive Church in all Ages, ought in reaſon to be believed as true.</p>
            <p>I acknowledge, were not theſe Articles of our Creed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly contained either in the expreſs Words, or in the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary concluſions of Scripture, or in the explications of the pureſt Ages of our Religion, the belief of them wou'd be irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, and theſe unwarrantably crowded upon the belief of a Chriſtian: And therefore, even in thoſe very Articles, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed our Reaſon, it is ſtill Reaſon which muſt juſtifie our Faith: What, is our Reaſon given us for no other end; than to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult for the eaſe and ſatisfaction of our Bodies, or muſt that moſt ſublime faculty of our Souls be no ways intereſs'd or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd for its own Happineſs and Salvation? Again, can we think the Divine Wiſdom had no deſign in dictating the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94785:9"/>or has he expreſs'd his intention to reach only the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and the Wiſe? Did not our Lord once make this the moſt expreſſive Argument, that the Meſſiah was come, <hi>viz. The poor have the Goſpel Preached unto them?</hi> And muſt it not ſeem very ſtrange, that Matters ſhou'd be ſo inverted ſince he is gone, and this very Goſpel left to us in Writing, that it is to be inſpected now only by Doctors and Philoſophers? Though the Poor have the Goſpel ſtill Preached unto them, yet the uſe of the Scriptures may well be regiſtred to make up thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and imperfections which our Preaching now abounds with, in reſpect of thoſe more powerful and efficacious Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>I know none of us who are able to Convert Three Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand with a Sermon; nor indeed, can we pretend to enforce any thing worthy of belief in you that hear us, but what we our ſelves fetch from that Fountain of heavenly Wiſdom, which is the written Word of God: And then, why every Man may not as well Read, as hear the Goſpel read to him; I leave to that bleſſed Spirit to determine, which exhorteth all Men to ſearch the Scriptures. No doubt, as God has given us Reaſon to make us capable of Underſtanding, and Glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Divine Majeſty, ſo has he given us his Scriptures alſo, on purpoſe to exalt and enlighten our Reaſon, and convince us all of the reaſonableneſs of our Religious Services; and I confeſs, I ſee not how that Man can be able to pay his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Service to God, who has taken up a belief in him without Reaſon; for let the Religion profeſſed by ſuch a Man be never ſo Holy and Pure, and true in its ſelf, ſtill in reſpect of ſuch a Profeſſor, this muſt be own'd rather to Chance and Fortune, than ſuch a choice and wiſdom as may affirm with the Bleſs'd Jeſus, <hi>We know what we Worſhip:</hi> For without Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, there can be no Belief, and without Belief, no true coming unto God: But further, what reaſonable Satisfaction can this be to any Man, to encourage him in his Perſeverance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94785:9"/>in his Religion in times of Tryals and Temptations; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, he has taken up his Religion by Chance, and though he knows not why, yet ſtill he is to be ſure that he is in the right.</p>
            <p>But can any thing here touch the Proſelytes of <hi>Rome,</hi> who, without troubling Scripture or Reaſon for the confirmations of their Evidence, tell us, they enjoy a far more inſallible Rock, and certainty of their Faith, to wit, the Voice and Teſtimony of the Church. In truth, if we ſearch into this Rock, it will appear no other than that Sandy Foundation, which was the choice of the fooliſh Builder: Let us reaſon the Caſe with ſome <hi>Roman</hi> Votary: Does thy Church, ſayeſt thou, tell thee thy Faith is true, then let me ask thee how thou knoweſt that the Church which tells thee ſo is true her ſelf; doeſt thou appeal to the Marks and Notes of a true Church, then I demand again, how doſt thou know what peculiar Marks and Notes are the Marks and Notes of the true Church? Or again, how is it become certain to thee, that all theſe peculiar Marks and Notes do particularly fit and agree with thy particular Church in all reſpects? He that gets over theſe Queſtions without Scripture and Reaſon, muſt be Maſter of more than a Jeſuitical ſlight and artifice; for this muſt be to judge of Notes without Judgment, to pronounce a concluſion without Premiſes; for where the concluſion is the reſult of Premiſes, there muſt needs be reaſoning: Indeed, this can be no other, than to reply, Why ſhe is true, becauſe ſhe is true: And yet I dare boldly affirm, they ſhall never be able to get further in the certainty of Faith, who ſhall firſt reject the Scriptures as too ambiguous and unintelligible; and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their Reaſon as a thing dangerous, and reducing all to a private Spirit. But they are not brought to a ſtand yet, they have behind a glorious reſerve, they will ſtill tell us they have Councils and Fathers on their ſide; but to expreſs the weakneſs of this hold, how many Volumes of Learn'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94785:10"/>are there extant, which remain ſo many monuments of the groundleſs vanity of their Plea from Fathers? and if the four firſt general Councils may be allow'd worthy of the name of Councils, we defie the moſt Artificial Crafts men of them all to produce thence but one line which may appear ſerviceable to the cauſe of Popery.</p>
            <p>But to leave this Conteſt with the Learned, muſt it not be ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in any unlearned Man to renounce the Scriptures, which were written on purpoſe for his Inſtruction in Religion, and which he may of himſelf be able both to read and underſtand, as to all matters of belief and practice, and betake himſelf to pleas from Fathers and Councils, when he is not able ſo much as to tell the Letters of that Language in which thoſe Fathers and Councils were written, when he can be able to judge neither when thoſe Fathers writ, nor yet what one Opinion they have left behind them: muſt there not be a much more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rional ſatisfaction from ſuch a plain Text of Scripture as this, <hi>Drink ye all of this,</hi> to invite us to receive the Cup, than a Thouſand pretended Quotations from ſuch Fathers and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils which the unlearn'd are able neither to diſprove nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, to affright us from the Cup, that we ſhou'd be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the plain real truths of the Goſpel; 'tis impoſſible but the real Doctrines of fallible Men will be liable to deceive us. But after all, is not this to relapſe and be found tampering with the dangerous conſequences of proteſtant reaſoning, thus to alledge Councils and Fathers: For why does any Man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to Councils and Fathers fancies, he makes them the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of his belief, at leaſt of the truth of that point in which he appeals to them? wou'd he believe as he does, if he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended he had no reaſon from their authorities to believe ſo, and then how does his Faith diſſer more from that of a private judgment, than the Faith of a credulous Proteſtant, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claies he believes thus and thus, becauſe he judges the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures enjoyn him to believe thus and thus; all the difference
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94785:10"/>that I can perceive between the two Churches here is this; The one, to wit, the Papiſt, Reaſons from the Teſtimonies of fallible Men; but the other, namely, the Proteſtant, from the aſſurances of the infallible Dictates of God's Holy Spirit. That which here determines the Belief in both, is no doubt one and the ſame thing, <hi>viz.</hi> Man's private Judgment, which influences the one to believe ſo and ſo, and the other to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thus and thus, becauſe it appears moſt reaſonable to them to believe ſo: And I appeal to any one of that Church, whether he wou'd thus abſolutely give up his Faith to the Church, did he not think he had great reaſon ſo to do; and then again, whether that Man which owns thus much, does not in great meaſure acknowledge himſelf a Judge of the Principles of his Religion; let them talk what they will, the Papiſt judges for himſelf as well as the Proteſtant; for if we are ſaid to judge, when we declare to believe the Scriptures upon the authority of an Univerſal Tradition, may not they be ſaid to judge, when they declare they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Church, upon the ſingle authority of her own aſſertion?</p>
            <p>If they pleaſe, they may deny what both they and we do practice; and indeed, what is not only undeniable, but what the very Voice and Commandment of God has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd us to perform; in one place, directing us to try all things, and hold faſt that which is good; in another place, believe not every Spirit, but try the Spirits whether they be of God or no: Again, be ye ready to render a reaſon of the hope that is in you, nay, laſtly, we have the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs approbation of our Saviour himſelf, telling us, <hi>If the Blind lead the Blind, they ſhall both fall into the Ditch,</hi> and again, <hi>why of your ſelves judge ye not what is right:</hi> Can any thing be more clear, than that the Holy Ghoſt in theſe places excites us to reſpect our own Judgment and Reaſon in the choice of our Religion: For, how ſhall that Man be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94785:11"/>able to render a Reaſon of his hope, who makes a Profeſſion of a hope upon no Reaſon at all? How ſhall he judge the Spirits that tries them not? Or again, how ſhall he make tryals, who profeſſes to uſe neither Judgment nor Reaſon in matters of Religion? Nay, further, how comes our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to wonder ſo much, why, <hi>Judge not of your ſelves what is right;</hi> if nothing be more diſagreeable to true Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, than a Man's own private Concluſions and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>I ſay again, theſe Texts muſt refer to the tryals of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and therefore we may bid much good may do them with their implicit Faith, which is as much as to declare as to my Religion. I believe what I know not, and I know not what I muſt believe; which is to approve the Spirits without trying; and to conclude them to be of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as enquiring what kind of Spirits they are of which belong to God: Nay, which is apparently to profeſs Doctrines, which 'tis impoſſible they ſhou'd render a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of, for without knowledge there can be no Reaſon given, and no Man will pretend to know that explicitly, of which he profeſſes purely an implicit Belief, nay, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps which he underſtands not that he does believe, till the Church upon an occaſion rubs up his Faith and Memory, and tells him he muſt, and he does believe it. I am ſure this is ſuch a kind of Faith, which Chriſt himſelf deteſted to impoſe; for we may obſerve, that he never recommended any thing to the belief of the <hi>Jews,</hi> but what he ſtill confirmed with ſuch Tokens as might convince the meaneſt Spectators of its Truth; nay, we find he taught his Diſciples many eſſential Doctrines before his Death, which they believed not, but did not Anathematize their incredulity, till they became able to bear them, till they had beheld that moſt convincing Demonſtration then remaining, even the irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible ſign of his Reſurrection: Nay, that nothing of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94785:11"/>might be wanting to the ſatisfying the Reaſon of Man, even after that glorious Demonſtration, he humbly condeſcended to let miſtruſtful <hi>Thomas</hi> thruſt his Fingers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very holes of the Nails, and behold the Prints in his Side.</p>
            <p>Is here any thing like the impoſition of an implicit Faith, or ſuch a groundleſs Belief as obliges us not only to abandon our Reaſon with all the ſtrongeſt Convictions of our Senſes, but alſo to renounce the helps even of the inſpired Writings of that bleſſed Comforter, which was ſent on purpoſe to lead us into all Truth: Since Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was pleaſed thus meekly to condeſcend in the giving ſatisfaction to our Infirmities, what kind of relation can that Church bear to him, which diſdains a ſubmiſſion to an Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, either by Reaſon, or the bleſſed Rule of God's own Word: I am ſure it muſt be a ſhrewd ſign, that that Church, which makes this refuſal, is reconcileable neither to Reaſon nor Scripture; for were ſhe agreeable to either, why ſhou'd ſhe ſo imperiouſly decline a tryal by the two moſt Godlike Principles we are enriched with, which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Scripture and Reaſon may be acknowledged to be; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it be any great diſgrace to the pureſt Church to be made appear conformable to them. I confeſs, I can't but admire the ſubtilty of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in uſurping thus an Authority above all Examination, ſince her Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Faith are ſuch, as far tranſcend the Explications either of Scripture or Reaſon, the cleareſt meaſures which God has left us to examine by: Is it not much the wiſeſt way to put off ſuch Commodities by the Groſs, which we are ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied won't bear a particular inſpection? Is there not much greater ſecurity to ſuch a Cauſe in an implicit Faith, which ſwallows down all at a lump, than ſuch an explicit one as may be curious and inquiſitive, and deſire the ſatisfaction of Senſe and Reaſon; I ſee no falſe ſtep here on their Churches
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94785:12"/>ſide, in point of Carnal Prudence and Worldly Policy, but methinks that muſt be an unintelligible Devotion indeed, which does thus contentedly enſnare his Soul for a Pig in a Poke, for what he is neither to ſcruple, nor yet to underſtand.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee upon what contradictory and irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable poſitions the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are founded at preſent: that they are as far from one another as Scripture and no Scripture, Reaſon and no Reaſon, Antiquity and Innovations, Truth and Falſhoods; and as the Churches ſtand at variance, ſo have the faithful Members of our Church upon all occaſions and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties appear'd in defiance of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Corruptions; it is not many years ſince moſt of us beheld, and all of us heard with what ſteadineſs and Devotion, with what Reſignation to the will of God, and diſdain to the pollutions of Men, the Members of our Church, like ſo many Illuſtrious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors withſtood the attempts and ſollicitations, the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and invitations of the Whoriſh Woman: Withſtood them, I ſay, even then, when many of the Members of our ſeparate Congregations, who had before ſhew'd themſelves moſt uneaſie in their fears of Popery, gave life and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to her growing hopes, by their unſeaſonable Addreſſes and Compliances. I ſpeak not this with a deſire to make ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of the weakneſs, or by way of inſult over the inconſtancy of our fellow Chriſtians now in Charity.</p>
            <p>I perſwade my ſelf they were rather outreach'd by the policies, than debauch'd by the principles of <hi>Rome,</hi> and there is nothing we ought all more heartily to pray for, or more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly endeavour than a mutual forgetfulneſs of all infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: but I ſpeak it with hopes, that as ſuch Proteſtants muſt acknowledge their error in ſiding with Popery then; ſo they will bluſh when they upbraid our Church as a Daughter of <hi>Babylon</hi> now: if Men wou'd but credit their own eyes, or give place to the arguments preſented to their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94785:12"/>own underſtandings, we need not appeal to other than our adverſaries themſelves, whether they can ſtill believe our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſervice to be (what ſome people do ignorantly miſcall it) Popery in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who remember the toleration and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty given to every Soul, to run as far out of our Church and the ſound of its divine ſervice as they pleaſed, managed by the artifice ſet on foot, and carry'd on by the influence of the Papiſts: if the way to <hi>Rome</hi> lies through a Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with our Church as ſuch Men dream, how come the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> (who are no ſtrangers to their own intereſts) to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Men out of our Communion as the readieſt road to Popery; had they ſeen with ſome Mens eyes amongſt us, and found any thing in our Communion which looks kind and ſerviceable to the cauſe of their own ſuperſtitions, 'tis not to be believed they wou'd ſo publickly have tempted all Men out of our Communion, with the alluring promiſes of the royal favour; I take that liberty and toleration then given by the Papiſtry, to be ſo manifeſt an argument and declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of that oppoſition which our Church, in every particular of its conſtitution bears to Popery, which, as every eye might diſcern it, ſo every well-meaning Man ought to be convinced by it, and retract his cenſures. The Papiſts knew well enough there wou'd be no enlarging their own, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out firſt thining our Churches, that the Maſs Book cou'd make no advances, whilſt the Common-Prayer ſtood in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; that the only probability they cou'd have of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any Proſelytes muſt be to get Men as far out of the boſom of our Church as poſſible.</p>
            <p>Methinks the pretences of ſome in ſeparation from us, who reproach our ſervice for Popiſh, and the practices of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts who were for drawing all Men out of our Communion as a bar to Popery, are very hard to be reconciled. The Concluſion from ſuch conſiderations muſt be this, Either the Papiſts underſtand not what makes up the Popiſh Religion,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94785:13"/>or the divine ſervice of our Church, which they appeared ſo eager to ſuppreſs and diſgrace, can be no friend to Popery.</p>
            <p>No, be not deceived my Beloved, the infamous names and characters, ſuch as Schiſmaticks, Hereticks, and the like, which they faſten upon us, and wherewith they attempt to blacken the brighteſt ſervices of all our holy miniſtrations; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſucceſſion of Plots, Stratagems, and Intrigues, which from Age to Age we have heard and ſeen formed by Papiſts againſt our holy reform'd Church, from the very firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of its eſtabliſhment, are and have been Arguments ſufficient to convince all Generations, of the irreconcilable diſtance between the Doctrines of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the principles of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> It muſt be aſtoniſhing therefore to conſider, what Sport and Paſtime <hi>Rome</hi> makes of us af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all: when ſhe ſtill ſo far intoxicates our heads by her ſnares of Diviſion, wherewith ſhe lyes in wait to deceive, and ſhatters all the foundations of our wiſdom and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, by thoſe winds of Doctrines which ſhe has raiſed and let looſe amongſt us, that we turn the wrath and diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection we profeſs to Popery, againſt that Church which has in ſo many, in ſuch illuſtrious inſtances manifeſted her ſelf the nobleſt bulwork againſt Popery, which we may with modeſty expreſs to be the only terror and envy of the Papiſts. Is not this the moſt formidable maſter-piece of thoſe deluders, to work up a profeſs'd enemy to ſuch a thoughtleſs zeal of indignation, as to make him fall foul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his friends, and under the pretence of wounding his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, give the mortal ſtroke to his own ſtrongeſt defence, which muſt be the accompliſhment of all thoſe (ſhou'd they ever have their end, which God forbid) who labour to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Church of <hi>England</hi> (whom <hi>Rome</hi> has ever treated as her moſt deadly foe) in order to the reforming Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſuch a manner wherein it may remain out of all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Popery; this is ſuch an undertaking wherein I am
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94785:13"/>ſure the hearts and hands of <hi>Romaniſts</hi> will never be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
            <p>The moſt weak and feeble Animals are ſeldom to be caught twice in the ſame Ginns, neither will the ſillieſt of Creatures run with open Eyes upon the naked Toil; nay, is it not a common proverbial Obſervation among us, that even the burnt Child dreads the Fire? and ſhall we with our ſinged Fingers catch at thoſe flames of Diſunion, wherewith our Adverſaries have ſo often reduced us to the moſt terrible Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, wherewith in the laſt Age they had well nigh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed both us and our Religion? When we have ſo fatally ſmarted under the Sting and Poiſon, ſhall we ſtill hug and cheriſh the Viper that breeds it? O no, let not us who really wiſh well to the true <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, who have experienced, and muſt be abundantly ſenſible of the Uncleanneſs and Abominations lodged in the inworks of <hi>Babylon;</hi> let not us, I ſay, fortifie her Walls by the works of our Hands, let us not proteſt againſt her Pollutions, and at the ſame time do the Drudgeries of her Tyranny; exclaim againſt her Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions, and pull down the Holy Temple of God's Truth, carry the name of Proteſtants and Reformiſts, and apply all our Parts, and Wiſdom, and Counſels in the undermining the ſacred foundations of that Proteſtant Church, which is the moſt ſolid and beauteous Pillar in the Reformation; no, I beſeech you my Beloved, in the name of our Lord Jeſus, that ye be rather cloathed with Meekneſs, and like that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Author and Finiſher of our Faith, put on Bowels of Love and Reconciliation, that this may appear before all the World to be the true, natural and proper Character of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant, That he is one, who is more large in his Charities, and humble in his Cenſures, more compaſſionate to his Brethren, and forgiving to his Enemies, more devoted to God, and inſeparable from the Services of his Church, than all other Sects and Profeſſions of Chriſtians whatever. To
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94785:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>conclude all, let not us, to whom God has vouchſafed the ineſtimable Bleſſing of a right Knowledge and Faith in Chriſt, ſuffer ſo glorious a Treaſure to lie dead and languid, and fruitleſs in our Souls for want of Works: Let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the World of the Excellency of our Faith and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in the Uprightneſs and Purity of our Lives, always bearing in our Minds this Deſcription of the Holy Apoſtle, in which he explains to us the end and intention of our Chriſtian Faith, ſaying, the Grace of God which bringeth Salvation, hath appeared to all Men, teaching us, that deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ungodlineſs, and Worldly Luſts, we ſhou'd live Soberly, and Righteouſly, and Godlily in this preſent World.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
